A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 2014-2018 (bulk 2014-2017)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of Administration, 2014-2018 (bulk 2014-2017)
The Library of Virginia
52171
5.35 cu. ft. (6 Boxes)
Virginia Secretary of Administration
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Restricted documents have been sealed within the collection.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Virginia Secretary of Administration on January 9, 2018.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Secretary of Administration is an appointed member of the Governor's Cabinet, and is subject to confirmation by the General Assembly. The Secretary of Administration oversees general government operations to ensure efficient and effective management of government resources. During Governor Terence Richard McAuliffe's term, the Secretary of Administration was responsible for the direction of, or had jurisdiction over: the Compensation Board, the Department of General Services, the Department of Human Resource Management, and the State Board of Elections. These agencies functions include the management of the state's real estate portfolio, serve as the state building official, administer employee policies and benefits, oversee procurement, promote business opportunities for Small, Women and Minority owned businesses, and supervise elections.
Nancy Rodrigues was appointed by Governor Terry McAuliffe to serve as Secretary of Administration on December 12, 2013. Rodrigues served as Virginia State Board of Elections Secretary from 2007 to 2011, following nearly a decade as the founding executive director of DRIVE SMART Virginia. This statewide non-profit private/public partnership organization's primary goal is reducing traffic fatalities and injuries; they declined significantly during Ms. Rodrigues' tenure and Virginia's safety-belt usage rate reached its then-highest-ever level.
Ms. Rodrigues received numerous prestigious honors during her career, including the Virginia Hispanic Chamber of Commerce Bridge Builder Award, the Award for Public Service from the National Highway Traffic Safety Administration, and the Gold Quill Award from the International Association of Business Communicator. She graduated with honors from Rutgers, the State University of New Jersey, where she received a B.A. in political science.
Scope and Content
The Secretary of Administration records consist of 6 archival boxes and are divided into 7 series. These records document the work of the Secretary of Administration during the McAuliffe administration and were created or collected between 2014 and 2018, though some documents in this collection predate these years.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Environmental Impact Studies, 2014-2018 (bulk 2014- 2017)
Series II. Real Property, 2015-2018
Series III. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies, 2014-2017
Series IV. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Office of the Secretary, 2014-2017
Series V. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Constituent Correspondence, 2014-2018
Series VI. Public Relations, 2014-2017
Series VII. Special Projects, 2014-2018 (bulk 2014-2017).
Contents List
- Series I. Environmental Impact Studies, 2014-2018., Extent: 2 boxes (2 cu. ft.) (Box 1-2)
  This series is housed in 2 boxes and is arranged chronologically by date of approval or disapproval of the memo, starting with box 2. Intellectual control and arrangement in this description was applied by processing archivist. This series contains environmental impact reports and studies created by state agencies prior to beginning construction projects. Section 10.1-1188 et seq., of the Code of Virginia requires that any state agency, institution or branch of government proposing to undertake a "major state project" prepare an environmental impact report. A "major state project" is defined as construction of a facility costing $100,000 or more, or the acquisition of land for which construction is contemplated. The Governor's approval of the report is required before any funds are expended.
  The report packets include the memorandum of approval (or approval with stipulations or disapproval); comments by the Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ) that include a description of the project, environmental impacts and mitigation, and regulatory and coordination needs; and various other memos and correspondence. The DEQ comments take into consideration the impact on water quality and wetlands, erosion and sediment control and storm water management, air quality, solid waste and hazardous waste management, natural heritage resources, wildlife resources, historic and archaeological resources, forestry and tree protection, geologic and mineral resources, energy conservation, transportation, the Chesapeake Bay Preservation Act, and local and regional concerns. Other agencies such as local governments, regional planning district commissions, the Department of Conservation and Recreation, Dept. of Historic Resources, Department of Transportation, Department of Game and Inland Fisheries and the Virginia Marine Resources Commission were also consulted and asked to comment on any potential problems.
  The projects range from small renovations and additions, to large scale construction efforts. The majority of the projects took place on university or community college campuses, but also include other state agencies such as the Western State Hospital, Dept. of Corrections, Dept. of Game and Inland Fisheries, and the Dept. of State Police.
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Jan. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Feb. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 March 6-11 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 March 14-25 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Apr. (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 May (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 June (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 July (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Aug-Sept. 12 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Sept. 18-24 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Oct. 1-21. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Oct. 22-31 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Nov. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Dec. 10-16 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2014 Dec. 16-29 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 Jan. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 March (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 Apr. (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 May (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 June (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 July (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 Aug. 6-13 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 Aug. 19-24 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 Sept. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 Oct. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 Sept.-Oct. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 Nov. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2015 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 Feb. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 March. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 May 2-5 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 May 6-17 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 May 19 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 May 20-25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 June 7-16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 June 20-27 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 July (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 Sept.-Oct. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2016 Dec. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2017 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2017 Feb.-March (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2017 Apr. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2017 May (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2017 June (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2017 July (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2017 Aug. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2017 Oct. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Environmental Impact Reports, 2018 Jan. (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series II. Real Property, 2015-2018., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  Real Property files, 2015-2018, are housed in 1 box (28 folders) and arranged chronologically. This series includes correspondence, deeds, leases, and memoranda, but the bulk is primarily recommendation forms and reports that document the disposition, funding, maintenance and operation of certain state buildings as well as other real property issues handled by the Department of General Services (DGS). The DGS Recommendation forms cover Deeds, Disposition of Surplus Property, Expense Leases, Income Leases, Purchase Agreements, Right of Way, Temporary Transfers, and Utility Easements.
  - Recommendations, 2015, Sept. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Recommendations, 2015, Oct. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Recommendations, 2015, Nov. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Recommendations, 2015, Dec. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Recommendations, 2016, Jan. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Recommendations, 2016, Feb. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Recommendations, 2016, March (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Recommendations, 2016, Apr. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Recommendations, 2016, May (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Recommendations, 2016, June (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Recommendations, 2016, July (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Recommendations, 2016, Aug. (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Recommendations, 2016, Sept. (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Recommendations, 2016, Oct. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Recommendations, 2016, Nov. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Recommendations, 2017, Jan. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Recommendations, 2017, Feb. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Recommendations, 2017, March (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Recommendations, 2017, Apr. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Recommendations, 2017, May (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Recommendations, 2017, June (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Recommendations, 2017, July (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Recommendations, 2017, Aug. (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Recommendations, 2017, Sept. (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Recommendations, 2017, Oct. (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Recommendations, 2017, Nov. (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Recommendations, 2017, Dec. (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Recommendations, 2018, Jan. (Box 3, Folder 28)
- Series III. Correspondence and Supporting Documentation: Assigned State Agencies,2014-2017., Extent: 1 boxes. (Box 3)
  This series is housed in 1 box (28 folders) and is arranged alphabetically by agency. These files include correspondence along with subject files and supporting materials such as briefs, meeting records, presentations, and reports of the state agencies under the office of the secretary of Administration: the Compensation Board, Department of General Services, Department of Human Resource Management, and the State Board of Elections.
  - Compensation Board: Executive Agreement, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Compensation Board: Fines and Fees Report (FY15), 2015 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Compensation Board: Fines and Fees Report (FY15), 2016 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Compensation Board: Mental Illness in Jails Report, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Compensation Board: Fines and Fees Report (FY16), 2016 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Compensation Board: Jail Cost Report (FY16), 2016 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - General Services: Bank Street Assessment, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - General Services: General Correspondence, 2014-2015 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - General Services: General Correspondence, 2016-2017 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - General Services: Excellence in Procurement, 2016-2017 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - General Services: Executive Agreement, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - General Services: Higher Education, 2014-2017 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - General Services: Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission (JLARC), 2014-2017 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - General Services: Surplus Property, 2014-2017 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Human Resource Management: Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), 2016 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Human Resource Management: Annual Salary Review (FY15) (JLARC), 2015 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Human Resource Management: Authorizations and Compensation Activities (FY18), 2018 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Human Resource Management: General Correspondence, 2014-2017 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Human Resource Management: Executive Order 41, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Human Resource Management: Executive Agreement - Wilson, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Human Resource Management: Reports of WOrkers' Compensation Program Settlements (FY16), 2016 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Human Resource Management: Reports of WOrkers' Compensation Program Settlements (FY17), 2017 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - State Board of Elections: Executive Agreement - Edgardo Cortes, 2014. (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - State Board of Elections: Concept of Operations (CONOPS), 2016 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - State Board of Elections: Risk Management Plan, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - State Board of Elections: General Registrar/Electoral Board (GREB), 2015 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - State Board of Elections: Fairfax County, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - State Board of Elections: Vice Chairman Clara Belle Wheeler, MD, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - State Board of Elections: Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission (JLARC) Review, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- Series IV. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Office of the Secretary, 2014-2017., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  This series is housed in 1 box (8 folders) and is arranged alphabetically by subject matter. This series includes incoming and outgoing correspondence, as well as subject files. Types of documentation includes correspondence, articles, briefs, meeting records, notes, and reports. The subject files accumulated by the Secretary document budgeting and financial statements, cabinet meetings and retreats, and other matters with which the Secretary was involved.
  - Election Process, 2014-2016 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - General Correspondence, 2014-2017 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Planning and Budget, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Planning and Budget, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Planning and Budget, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Planning and Budget, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Procurement, 2015-2016 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - State Fraud, Waste, and Abuse Hotline, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 65)
- Series V. Correspondence and supporting documentation: Constituent Correspondence, 2014-2017., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  This series is housed in 1 box (2 folders) and is arranged chronologically. This series includes correspondence that was originally addressed to Governor McAuliffe and then referred to the Secretary of Administration for response on behalf of the Governor, as well as letters addressed directly to the Secretary. Correspondence is from the general public, as well as from business and civic leaders, college and university officials, and state and federal government officials and legislators. Correspondence is also from members of the Virginia General Assembly. This series also includes copies of outgoing responses.
  - Constituent correspondence, 2014-2015 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Constituent correspondence, 2016-2017 (Box 3, Folder 67)
- Series VI: Public Relations,2014-2018 (bulk 2014-2017)., Extent: 1 box. (Box 3)
  This series is housed in 1 box (5 folders) and is arranged chronologically. This series documents the Secretary's involvement in official functions, as well as the planning, development, and carrying out of public relation activities or visits sponsored by the Secretariat. Invitations and related planning documentations make up the bulk of this series.
  - Invitations, 2014 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Invitations, 2015 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Invitations, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Invitations, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Invitations: no Date (Year) ca. 2014-2017 (Box 3, Folder 72)
- Series VII: Special Projects,2014-2017., Extent: 2 boxes (1.35 cu. ft.) (Box 4-5)
  This series is housed in 2 boxes and is arranged alphabetically. The bulk of this series contains communications, reports, agendas, and other material supporting various specific projects of the Secretary.
  Box 5 includes about a dozen architectural renderings of the proposed design for the Executive Mansion's addition in 2015. This addition was meant to comply with the Americans with Disabilities Act, making the governor's mansion more accessible. The illustrations are printed on styrofoam boards housed in the box (5) outside of folders.
  - Awards/Employees, 2015-2016 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Camp Pendleton, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Center for Innovative Technology, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Conservation and Recreation, 2015 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cycling Championships, 2014-2015 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - eVA (Procurement Marketplace), 2014 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Fort Monroe, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - iBook (Department of Education), 2014 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - James Monroe Memorial, 2015 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Pelham Chapel Confederate Memorial, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - State Property Buildings, 2014-2016 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Small, Women-Owned, and Minority Businesses (SWaM)/Small Businesses, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Virginia Information Technologies Agency (VITA), 2016 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Women's Monument: Overview, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Women's Monument: Proposal, 2016 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Women's Monument: General, 2016-2017 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Women's Monument: Schematic Design Report, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Executive Mansion Americans with Disabilities Act Modification Architectural Renderings, 2015 (Box 5)